Guide to the Balmori Associates Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Balmori Associates records
1941-2014
1970-2014
MS 1885
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
26.5
36 boxes
15.5
The records are comprised of drawings, photographs, correspondence, notes, slides, audiovisual, and printed material pertaining to the work of Balmori Associates, including documentation of projects in the United States and Europe. Also included are writings, both published and unpublished, by principal Diana Balmori, circa 1970-2004.
Balmori Associates
Custodial History
Gift of Balmori Associates, 2006 and 2015-2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research, except for electronic records, which are closed until processed.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers withing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Biographical / Historical
Balmori Associates is an urban and landscape design firm in New York City founded by Diana Balmori (1932-2016) in 1990. Balmori Associates is recognized for their interfacing between landscape and architecture. Through research, collaboration and innovation, Balmori Associates is looking to explore and expand the boundaries between nature and structure. Their approach to developing public spaces is rooted in design ideas, coupled with an understanding of environmental, social and physical needs. Their application of innovative designs to the study of the social functions of green roofs, floating islands and temporary landscapes has created a signature and functional aesthetic establishing them as leaders in the field of urban design and the creation of new forms of public space.
Source: Balmori Associates
Arrangement
The records are arranged in two series: I. Project records, 1987-2014 (bulk). II. Writings, 1970-2006.
Scope and Contents
The records are comprised of drawings, photographs, correspondence, notes, slides, audiovisual, and printed material pertaining to the work of Balmori Associates, including documentation of projects in the United States and Europe. Also included are writings, both published and unpublished, by principal Diana Balmori, circa 1970-2004.
Architecture, American -- 20th Century; Landscape architecture; Balmori, Diana, 1932-2016; Balmori Associates
- Project Records, 1941-2014; 1987-2014; Series I
  - Vassar College, 1987-2005
    - Art Center, 1990-1993
      - Early sketches and schematic design, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      - Design development and presentation drawings, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
      - Construction documents and working drawings, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Avery Courtyard, 1998-2005
      General
      Project statement: The design of the Frances K. Fergusson Courtyard serves to anchor three buildings in a nondescript amorphous space and to give the students from the new Drama School a place to gather, to watch a performance or a film, or to just hang out.
      The rectangular courtyard, 80 by 140 feet, is sunken 1.5 feet into the earth. The inner surface is sodded, and the concrete wall around the perimeter clad in copper. The copper has since turned brown, now resembling the color of the earth. Gradually it will tarnish to green and feel closer to the grass on the surface of the bottom of the space. A ramp leads down into the space from each end of the rectangle. Students perch along the comfortable edge as on a bench. The space has become especially popular on winter days, when the southern side of the courtyard receives sun late into the afternoon. The three surrounding buildings feel anchored by the space. A Breuer designed dormitory sits on one of the long sides of the rectangle. On the opposite side of the rectangle, an evergreen hedge, which will be shaped over time, shields the courtyard from a view of the lower service area. The hedge also serves to protect the courtyard from north winds. LED lights create a soft glow in the courtyard at night, also serving to make the edge of the courtyard visible.
      - Project statement, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Minutes, 2001 October (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Site photos, Circa 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Slides, 2001 April (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Lighting, 2005-2006 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Scope and Contents
        Includes correspondence, photos, and research.
      - Electronic records
        Conditions Governing Access
        Closed until processed.
    - Computer Center, Circa 1992 (Box 5)
    - Loeb Art Center Sculpture Garden, 1987-2003
      Project Statement: The two open spaces on this project--the Briarcombe Sculpture Courtyard and the Hildegarde Krause Baker Sculpture Garden--were designed for the Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center at Vassar College in Poughkeepsie, New York. The Briarcombe Sculpture Courtyard is a small, graveled courtyard beside the long glassed-in gallery walk to the museum. This area is used for sculpture exhibits. By the side of the museum, the Hildegarde Krause Baker Sculpture Garden was created to become a sculpture garden over time, its surrounding walls enclosing a gigantic, tricolor beech tree, which was left in place to be a jewel in the pathway of the garden. The center island contains dark planting material, the outer planting beds light colored material. Screens of wisteria and clematis vines shield the approach to the garden. The forecourt to the garden, where large sculptures can be exhibited, is partially paved in brick. This space is marked by three screens, which create a backdrop for the sculpture before them. The screens also create a barrier to keep the eye from traveling beyond the sculpture. Two slots cut out between the three screens allow a view of the back wall and the beech tree. The darker background of the back wall also separates the forecourt from the garden itself.
      Balmori's design team included Peter Viteretto, Christopher Siefert, Robert Milchrest and Martha Burgess. The architect of the Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center was Cesar Pelli & Associates.
      Entry and Sculpture Courtyards: 2,900 square feet.
      Sculpture Garden: 8,600 square feet.
      The project was completed in 1994.
      - Project statement, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Project budget, 1991 February (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Project description, Circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1991 November-1993 August (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
      - Email correspondence, 2002 October-Nov, 2003 May (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Photographs
        - Vassar Campus prints, Circa 1991 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
        - Site photos, Circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
        - Drawings, Circa 1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
        - Models: prints, Circa 1991 (Box 4, Folder 16)
        - Plant material: prints, 1989 August (Box 4, Folder 17)
        - Construction: prints, Circa 1991 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
        - Completed project: prints, negatives, 1994 May-Jun, 1998 Sep, 2001 April (Box 4, Folder 20-22)
        - Sculpture Garden (completed): prints, Circa 1994 May (Box 4, Folder 23)
        - Negatives, transparencies, contact sheet, Circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Slides
        - Slide list, Circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 25)
        - Site photos, Circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 26)
        - Drawings, Circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 27)
        - Models, 1991 February (Box 4, Folder 28)
        - Tree selection and tagging, 1992 November (Box 4, Folder 29)
        - Master plans drawing and construction, Circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 30)
        - Sculpture Garden: Paved area, 1994 Nov, 1996 May (Box 4, Folder 31)
        - Sculpture Garden: Planted area, 1996 May, 1997 October (Box 4, Folder 32)
        - Entry court, 1992 Sep, 1996 May (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Electronic records
    - Master Plan, 1991
      - Base materials, 1987-1991 (Box 6–7)
      - Early sketches and schematic design, Circa 1991 (Box 8)
      - Design development and presentation drawings, Circa 1991 (Box 9)
  - Princess Diana Memorial Fountain, 2001-2006
    Project description: Eleven international teams of artists, architects and landscape architects were invited to submit designs for a memorial fountain for Princess Diana by the Serpentine Stream in Hyde Park, London, England. In addition to Diana Balmori, they were: Zaha Hadid; Anish Kapoor and Future Systems; Kathryn Gustafson (the only other landscape architect); Tony Fretton; Terry Farrell; William Pye; Rik Nys; Julian Opie; Adam Carouso and Peter St. John; Tom Lonsdale and Thomas Heatherwick. The jury consisted primarily of art curators with one representative from the Parks Department. The panel chose three finalists: Balmori, Gustafson, and Kapoor. After three months of deliberation, the jurists were unable to come to an agreement. Britain's Cultural Secretary, Tessa Jowell, intervened to resolve the impasse, awarding the project to Gustafson.
    In December 2001, Balmori spent a week at the site formulating a basic scheme and creating a series of hand drawings, which included sketches made on site. Balmori's design team included Paul Butkus, Adrienne Cortez, Julie Farris, Javier Gonzalez, Nathan Howe, Cecilia B. Martinic and Mark Thomann. In addition, the group worked with an English landscape architect and ecologist, Andrew Grant, who provided expertise on mosses. Other partners on the project included Long & Kentish (architects); Patrick Bellow/Atelier 10 (green systems/hydrology); and Sam Price (structural engineer). The scheme consisted of a fountain in the Serpentine, where a surface of still water would be surrounded by moving water. The different qualities of the two waters would create a dramatic contrast: the still water surface glassy, reflective; the other surface broken by the water's motion. The fountain would be fed from Serpentine water used for irrigating plants and moss on the hills surrounding the stream and returned to the fountain after being cleaned en route by the plants. The water would be cleaned en route to the fountain. This component of Balmori's design observed Princess Diana's concern for the environment, enacting, in a sense, a rite of purification of the Serpentine.
    - Project statement, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Diana Balmori's site sketchbook, 2001 December (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Competition information, 2001 November-December (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Site history - Background research, Circa 2004 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Firm profiles - project directory, 2001 July-October (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2001 October-2002 May (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
    - Project images, 2002 January-July (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Includes elevations, plans, diagrams, sections, renderings, etc..
    - Presentation drawing, Circa 2002 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Research, Circa 2002 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Images of design reference model, Circa 2002 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Text, 2002 January (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Photographs: existing site, 2001-2002 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Extra images, 2001 December-2002 July (Box 10, Folder 14)
      Includes photocopies, sketches, notes, plans, color printouts, etc.
    - Sample layouts, Circa 2002 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Administrative records, 2001 December-2002 January (Box 10, Folder 16)
      Includes expense vouchers, receipts; photocopies of packing slips, fax forms, etc.
    - Publicity, 2002 Jul, 2004 May (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Model, Circa 2005; physical model: bronze and glass (approx. 15-1/2" x 13" x 2") (Box 11)
    - Electronic records
  - Silvercup Studios - Green Roofs, Circa 2003-2006
    Project description: The project for the roof of the Silvercup Studios in Long Island City emerged from a proposal Diana Balmori submitted to the Long Island City Business Development Corporation (LICBDC) in Long Island City, Queens, in 2002 for greening the neighborhood, given its renown as the "asthma corridor." Directly beside the Queensboro Bridge (to Manhattan), Silvercup is situated in the worst section of this polluted district. Balmori and her team (which included Sarah Wayland-Smith and Mark Thomann) saw an opportunity to use Long Island City's many large, flat-roofed buildings-known as "pancake buildings"-calculating that if all of these surfaces were made "green," the area would be 667 acres, approximately the size of Brooklyn's Prospect Park.
    The first to express interest in the green roof project were the owners of a high-end furniture fabrication shop, Donald Gratz, and his wife, the urban critic and writer, Roberta Brandes Gratz. The shop is also located right next to the Queensboro Bridge. The green roof proposal also sparked the interest of the president of Silvercup Studios, Stuart Match Suna. Suna suggested that Balmori, with Silvercup, seek funding from green-oriented institutions. After more than a year, the group was awarded a $500,000 grant from Clean Air Communities, a non-profit organization devoted to reducing air pollution and increasing energy efficiency in New York City. Silvercup furnished engineering and architectural services, and Balmori Associates designed the green roof using a modular system to cover over 35,000 square feet of roof space on top of Studios X, B and 4.
    The plantings of different types and varieties of sedums on Silvercup's non-accessible roofs were purposefully selected for their color contrast to provide greater visibility from the Queensboro Bridge and from its on/off ramps on the Queens side. Cloth strips of brilliant colors were added as another way to increase the roofs' visibility. Such a high profile location has had the added benefit of letting the project serve as an advertisement for green roofs in general. Unfortunately, due to scheduling issues at Silvercup, the planting could only occur in August 2005, a month ill-suited for planting. The sedums were planted as 2-inch plugs, and by the summer of 2006, the roof was approximately 80% covered.
    - Project statement, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - 00 Funding applications
      - Clean Air Communities, 2003 July-2004 October (Box 10, Folder 19)
        Includes correspondence, application, request for proposal, proposal.
      - NYSERDA (New York State Energy Research and Development Authority), 2003 September (Box 10, Folder 20)
        Includes proposal and support documents.
    - 01 Project directory, 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - 02 Contract, 2004 November-2005 March (Box 10, Folder 22)
      Includes support documents.
    - 03 Client, 2004 April-2005 October (Box 10, Folder 23)
      Includes correspondence, e-mails, telephone logs, and schedules.
    - 04 Minutes, 2004 April-November (Box 10, Folder 24)
      Client, Balmori.
    - 05 Consultants
      - Landscape contractor, 2005 March-October (Box 10, Folder 25)
      - Associated architect, 2004 May-2005 March (Box 10, Folder 26)
      - Silvercup Studios, 2004 May-2005 September (Box 10, Folder 27)
      - Manufacturers, 2004 May-2005 April (Box 10, Folder 28)
      - Monitoring: EarthPledge, 2004 May-2005 June (Box 10, Folder 29)
      - Monitoring alternatives, 2004 May (Box 10, Folder 30)
      - Nursery specialist, 2005 March-May (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - 07 Fees, 2004 November-2005 September (Box 10, Folder 32)
      Includes budget tracking and invoices.
    - 08 Materials, 2005 June (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - 09 Specifications, 2005 March (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - 10 Background research, 2002 September-2003 July (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - 01 Existing drawings, 2003 September (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - 02 Design reference, 2003 July (Box 10, Folder 37)
      Includes lay-out and design data.
    - 04 Schematic design [Phase 2], 2004 December (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - 05 Design development [Phase 3], Circa 2004 (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - 06 Construction drawings, 2005 February-March (Box 10, Folder 40)
      Contains original bid package.
    - 01 Press releases, 2005 May, September (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - 02 Selected project images - Phases of project: documentary photographs, 2004 October-2005 November (Box 10, Folder 42)
      Includes copyright information.
    - 02 Press releases: press correspondence, 2005 August-October (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - 03 Public events
      - Event schedule, summary, presentation materials, 2005 September (Box 10, Folder 44)
      - Coordination
        - Event planning notes, 2005 May-September (Box 10, Folder 45)
        - Invitation lists, 2005 September (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - 04 Publications, 2005 August-2006 September (Box 10, Folder 47)
      - Long Island (Green) City, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Electronic records
  - St. Louis Riverfront, 2001-2006
    Project description: The intent of our St. Louis Riverfront design is to create a vibrant, innovative riverfront with strong connections to the Arch site, to the city of St. Louis and to the Mississippi River. After Diana Balmori presented four possible schemes, the client, Great Rivers Greenway, chose the fourth and most ambitious of the schemes: Terraces and Islands. This scheme called for a cluster of floating islands on the Mississippi River with programmatic features such as restaurants, support facilities, and a possible natural history pavilion on the islands. The riverfront is terraced with several levels of pedestrian paths and places to sit and relax. At high water levels, when the lower terraces are submerged, the floating islands will rise with the water and still be accessible from pontoon walkways. This scheme exploits the dynamism of the shifting water levels and maintains accessibility to the river as it fluctuates.
    The waterfront development will occur in two phases. Phase I will focus on the 3/4-mile stretch between the Eads and Poplar Street bridges. The area will be bound by Leonor K. Sullivan Boulevard on the west; by the middle of the Mississippi River on the east; by Biddle Street on the north; and by Chouteau Avenue on the south. Phase II moves on to an adjacent 3/4 mile stretch. The project area is in two sections of Leonor K. Sullivan Boulevard and the riverfront. The northern section is bound by Eads Bridge north to Biddle Street. The southern section is bound by Poplar Street Bridge south to Chouteau Avenue.
    Four principles guide the design of the St. Louis Riverfront:
    Experience the nature and presence of the river. This first principle is derived from the site's location on the Mississippi River. Above all else, the idea is to offer as many ways as possible in which the public can experience and interact with the water along this channeled waterfront. The potential for edge treatments, layers and platforms that expose the phenomena of the river's flow at the various water levels are the secret to a successful design experience. Creating experiences will initiate interaction with the river and define it as a place.
    Create new connections. The second principle involves the identification of all connections from physical, visual, social and temporal perspectives. Physical connections include the Eads Bridge, Downtown St. Louis, the Arch Grounds, Laclede's Landing, Chouteau's Landing and the Greenways comprising the River Ring. Visually, the design should directly link to the river back to Downtown and to the Arch as it frames westward views and back to the east. Socially, connections must include as many constituencies as possible for true community redevelopment. Temporal connections should be based on research of historical elements and events, current events, future development and the daily and seasonal fluctuations of the landscape and the river.
    Develop new spaces. The third principle understands that different physical spaces and transportation modes can uncover new functions and opportunities for the riverfront. The bridges and river could offer new means of water transportation and pedestrian crossings by way of the Eads Bridge or public excursion boats. These new spaces and transportation modes are examples of strategies that will provide a more accessible waterfront - while animating it with life and activity.
    Complement the City. The last principle implies that design should enhance what is already happening within the city, not compete with it. Many will feel that the design should provide a unique contrast to the arch grounds or that the riverfront should be an extension of the arch grounds itself to the water. The design process will determine this direction. The design idea is that the site is urban and is a part of revitalizing downtown. Urban design connections from the riverfront to the city are a necessary step in complementing the two.
    Budget constraints and permitting reduced the number of islands. These ecologically and aesthetically important islands create habitat and green space on a hard edged waterfront which endures a 40-foot fluctuation in water levels with strong currents carrying large-scale debris. In addition to the remaining islands, floating triangular vegetation mats will populate the two bays created in the space between the southern docks and terraces. These mats, like the floating islands, serve both ecological and aesthetic purposes. The mats can be colonized with specialized microbes that help clean the water, and the roots of the plants growing on the mats are valuable food for fish and other aquatic animals. The vegetation itself is habitat for birds and insects. Aesthetically, the Triangle Islands are another means of bringing life to the edge of the terraces. The diversity of plant life on the Triangular Islands will also be an important education tool for the ecological learning center on the southern terraces. Programmatic elements originally developed for the islands are shifted to land and will be organized into five nodes, creating centers of activity separated by contemplative landscape spaces.
    To avoid problems with river debris associated with structures anchored in the water, the terraces will be cantilevered, a 'feat of engineering' reminiscent of the ingenuity of the arch design and construction. The terraces will be made of a self supporting mesh, a structure without visible structural support. This will allow the surface to be transparent and prevent the lower space from becoming dark and unwelcoming. Additionally the structure must be able to withstand yearly flooding.
    Three bridges on the site will expand the experience of the river front by allowing visitors to walk over the river. These structures are also to be beautifully engineered. The pedestrian bridge to the north will take the profile of the arch and have a stainless steel underside with decking on the surface.
    - Project statement, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 02 Contract, 2005 May-2006 August (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 03 CIient: correspondence, 2005 February-November (Box 12, Folder 3-7)
    - 04 Minutes
      - Consultant coordination, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Client minutes, 2005 July-December (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - 05 Consultants
      - Fluidity, 2005 November-2006 January (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Engineers, 2005 April-July (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - CDG engineers, 2005 September (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Moffat and Nichol, Circa 2005 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Permitting, 2006 January-February (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Monitoring, 2006 September (Box 12, Folder 15)